<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Duplies to the petition and replyes given in to the Commission of Parliament for Fines and Forefaultures, by Alexander Munro of Bear-Crofts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2647A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174884</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981645</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2820:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Duplies to the petition and replyes given in to the Commission of Parliament for Fines and Forefaultures, by Alexander Munro of Bear-Crofts</title>
                  <author>Monroe, Alexander, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monroe, Alexander, fl. 1691.</term>
               <term>Clerks of court --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Courts --  Scotland --  Corrupt practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:180207:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180207:1"/>
            <head>DUPLIES To the PETITION and REPLYES given in to the COMMISSION of PARLIAMENT For FYNES and FOREFAULTURES, By <hi>Alexander Monro</hi> of <hi>Bear Crofts.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THIS Petition being a pretence to an Office <hi>impetrate</hi> contrare to the expreſs Terms of an Act of Parliament, and without payment of a <hi>ſixpence,</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Petitioner having reaped the profit for ſix years together; He thereafter <hi>freely Renounced</hi> and <hi>Overgave</hi> it in favours of <hi>Hayſtoun,</hi> upon payment of ſeven Thouſand Merks. It is no wonder if the grounds of it be now urged, and debated with as little Reaſon and Argument, as the claim it ſelf was firſt intented with regard to Law and Juſtice, for the Printed Replyes reſume the Defences, and cite the Text of the <hi>Roman Law</hi> with ſo much diſingenuity, making ſuch groſs and affected miſapplications and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and illiterate inferences; Firſt, ſetting up a ſhaddow of Fear and Force, and then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceing a nauſeous volum of impertinent citations againſt it, that it ſeems the Petitioner (who could have replyed much better himſelf) has referred them to ſome of his Lawyers, who had only the advantage to read more Catalogues, and profeſs more Law of deſign to <hi>embroile the caſe,</hi> and to <hi>teach</hi> the Lawyers imployed for the Clerks no other point of <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> then to miſtake their Defence by his Example.</p>
            <p>It will be needleſs to trouble the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> by repeating here the matter of Fact in the Anſwers, ſeing the Anſwers are in the hands of the Honourable Members, nor is it neceſſar to reſum the Dilator defences, already proponed, but only to add this farder, which may be conſidered as a Dilator, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſince the Petitioner has neither Conſigned nor Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the price he received, his Lybel ſhould be caſt, and the Defenders not oblieged to Anſwer to it, as was ſolemnly Decided on the 6th of <hi>July</hi> 1543. the Laird of <hi>Waughtoun</hi> againſt <hi>Sinclair</hi> of <hi>Steinſtown,</hi> and on the 26th of <hi>June</hi> 1576, <hi>Mackilvain</hi> againſt <hi>Crawford;</hi> And therefore the Defenders ſhall endeavour ſhortly to Duply to what is alleaged in the Reply againſt the perremptor Defences.</p>
            <p>Where 1mo: It is denyed, That the Government can diſpoſe of private Mens Rights, for the publick Utility, upon giving the private Party a reaſonable Recompence for their loſs, which was never before denyed by any Doctor, and is allowed by the practice of This and all other Nations, eſpecially as to the Diſpoſing or Regulating of publick Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Was not the Office of <hi>Juſtice Deputes</hi> ſuppreſſed, and the <hi>Juſtiaciary</hi> turned in a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:180207:2"/>
to five of the Ordinary Senators of the <hi>Colledge of Juſtice,</hi> when Mr. <hi>William Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray,</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Preſton</hi> had Gifts of the ſaid Office of being <hi>Juſtice Deputes</hi> during life, without alleadging any crime againſt them; or giving them any recompence for their loſs? And twenty other inſtances might be given of the like caſes, even when there was no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of any Law againſt the Conſtitution, as there is a clear and poſitive Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment founded on in this caſe, if it were not deſtroyed by the double Cannon-ſhot at it by the Reply, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1mo. That there is no ſuch Act of Sederunt, nor Act of Parliament; becauſe the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders acknowledge, the Record containing the Act of Sederunt is a way, and conſequently the Act of Parliament muſt fall, being only relative to the Act of Sederunt; <hi>Et non creditur Referenti niſi conſtiterit de relato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a ſort of reaſoning unworthy of a <hi>School-boy,</hi> much leſs of a <hi>Doctor of Law,</hi> as the Replier pretends to be: For ſeing the Act of Sederunt ſubſcribed by the whole Lords is extant, the abſtracting of the Record will not make it Null. 2do. <hi>Eſto,</hi> That both the Record, and Act of Sederunt were abſtracted, will that extinguiſh the force of the Act of Parliament, which does not only ratifie the Act of Sederunt, but declares the ſame to have the Force and Authority of an Act of Parliament? and that none may pretend Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; The whole Tenor of it is <hi>verbatim</hi> repeated in the Act of Parliament, and made a part of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But the Replyer finding that this would not do the Buſineſs, the Act of Parliament muſt be found Null, by its not being inſert in the Index of the unprinted Acts. Which 1mo. is moſt Irrelevant. 2do. It is moſt falſe, as any that will be at the trouble to read the Index will find.</p>
            <p>And as his laſt effort againſt the ſaid Act, he will have it in deſuetude, and preſcrived by an Argument of a piece with the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That on the 25 of <hi>July</hi> 1632, Mr <hi>Alexander Gibſon,</hi> and <hi>John Gibſon</hi> his Brother, were preſented conjunct Clerks in one Office, by Sir <hi>John Hamiltoun</hi> Clerk Regiſter, and accordingly admitted by the Lords; and upon the 1 <hi>June</hi> 1636, Mr <hi>John</hi> and Mr <hi>William Hay</hi> his Son, were preſented conjunct Clerks in one Office by Sir <hi>John Hay</hi> Clerk Regiſter, and accordingly admitted by the Lords, and that ever ſince there has been two Clerks in each Office.</p>
            <p>The matter of Fact, as appears by the Record, was, That Mr <hi>Alexander Gibſon</hi> in the 1632 being ſole Clerk; deſigned to have his Brother <hi>John Gibſon</hi> joyned with him, and did dimite the Office in the hands of Sir <hi>John Hamilton,</hi> to the effect he might grant a new Gift in favours of his Brother <hi>John Gibſon</hi> and him, the longeſt liver of the two; which was accordingly done. And in the Year, 1636. Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> and Mr <hi>Alexander Hay</hi> his eldeſt Son being conjunct Clerks, Mr <hi>Alexander</hi> the Son dyed, and Mr <hi>John</hi> the Father makes a Dimiſſion of the Office in the Hands of Sir <hi>John Hay</hi> Clerk Regiſter, for his granting a new Gift in favours of himſelf, and <hi>John Hay</hi> his other Son the longeſt liver, which was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly done; Both which Gifts proceed expreſly on the conſent of the Incumbent, in the terms of the Act of Sederunt, and Act of Parliament; and conſequently are very fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought in to prove that the ſaids Acts were in deſuetude and preſcribed; And the firſt inſtance that can be given of placing two Clerks in one Office, without the conſent of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180207:2"/>
Incumbent, was in <hi>Iune</hi> 1649. (when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were invading the Kingdom, and all things in diſorder) that Sir <hi>Archibald Iohnſtoun</hi> of <hi>Wariſton</hi> did preſent Mr. <hi>David</hi> and Mr. <hi>Iohn Hayes</hi> conjunct Clerks in one Office; And to infer by that ſingle inſtance, That the Act of Parliament was in deſuetude, or that it did preſcrive betwixt the 1649. and 1661. or 1669, argues more Confidence than Judgement; So that the great foundation of the Reply, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Act of Sederunt and the Act of Parliament were in deſuetude, and preſcrived, falling, all the Superſtructer muſt fall in conſequence, and the <hi>Kings Letter appointing the Clerks to be regulate according to the ſaids Acts,</hi> will not import injuſtice, much leſs Concuſſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Learned Author</hi> of the Reply is in a miſtake, to pretend that the Anſwerer alleadges, the Lord <hi>Tarbat</hi> was the firſt that procured a Libertie to admit more Clerks then one in each Office; For all along its acknowledged, That Sir <hi>Archibald Primeroſes</hi> Gift did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe import that Liberty; But all that is contended is, That the Lord <hi>Tarbat</hi> was the firſt that did exerciſe that Liberty according to Law <hi>viz.</hi> By conjoyning only upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs conſent of the Incumbents in the Office; For, if the Regiſter might conjoin one without conſent, there can no rational ground be given why he might not conjoin three or four in each Office: So that the cauſe of Deputing one or more in each Office, will either run too farr, or muſt be regulat by the Act of Parliament, and the Intereſt and Conveniency of Lieges, of which the Lords of Seſſion are the only proper Judges. And it is hoped it will not be pleaded, That <hi>the King could diſpenſe with the Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> And the reaſon why the Lords of Seſſion did think it convenient, that there ſhould be no more then one Clerk in one office, unleſs the other Clerk were brought in at the Deſire, and with the Conſent of the Incumbent, was by reaſon of the prejudice that the Liedges might ſuſtain through the delay it might occaſion in the diſpatch of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, by the Debates and Quarrellings that might ariſe betwixt two Clerks in one Office, that were not in a good underſtanding together, whereof the Petitioner is a <hi>living Inſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is then apparent that His Majeſties Letter being conform to the ſtanding Law of the Kingdom, neither it, nor the Act of Sederunt following thereupon, can import any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice as to the Petitioner; But on the contrair, Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> had better ground to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, That the Lords ſentence, <hi>appointing him to pay</hi> 7000 <hi>Merks,</hi> was unjuſt, ſeing the Petitioner was impoſed upon him contrair to Law; then the Petitioner has to alleadge that the 7000 Merks was not a reaſonable Compoſition, being more than ever before that time was payed for any of theſe Imployments. And the vaſt difference betwixt <hi>Tarbat</hi> his bringing in of Conjuncts in each Office, and Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> his bringing them in does clearly appear, in that the one was done in the expreſs terms of the Act of Parliamenr, and conform to Law; and the other expreſly contrair to Law, which was fully conſidered by the Parliament 1685, wherein what <hi>Tarbat</hi> did, was approven and rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, not in courſe, but by a ſpecial Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> which is not <hi>Declaratorie,</hi> but is <hi>Statuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and yet not <hi>Derogatory</hi> from the Act 1621; for as the Act 1621, allowes only one Clerk in each Office, without conſent of the Incumbent; ſo the Act 1685, allowes only of two with conſent; and ſo ſecures that the Regiſter ſhould not be able to bring in more then two in each Office, albeit he ſhould procure the Incumbents conſent, which ſeemed to be unclear by the Act 1621.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180207:3"/>To the ſecond Defence, on the <hi>Brocard,</hi> That in <hi>dub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> melior eſt cauſa poſſidentis,</hi> It is Replyed, That the Petitioner in point of Right was <hi>prior tempore,</hi> and therefore <hi>potior jure;</hi> And that the poſſeſſion of the preſent Clerks can avail them nothing, in reſpect of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent way that the Petitioner <hi>deſiit poſſidere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which it is Duplyed, That it is true <hi>caeteris paribus qui prior eſt tempore potior eſt jure;</hi> But in this caſe (tho there were no ſuch thing as the Act of Parliament) the advantage of the poſſeſſion would make the difference, and preferr the Clerks; And the Law does indeed provide, That <hi>qui dol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſiit poſſidere,</hi> cannot thereby better his own caſe, which may be the Petitioners; but unleſs it could be proven that the Clerſhip were not in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſio,</hi> or had <hi>vitium rei furtiva,</hi> this advantage muſt by Law follow the poſſeſſion, that <hi>in dubio</hi> it prefers the Poſſeſſor; And it is obſervable, that albeit by the Law of the twelve Tables <hi>rei furtivae aeterna fuit authoritas;</hi> Yet the <hi>Praetorian</hi> Law in the Edict, <hi>quod metus cauſa,</hi> neither did nor could extend <hi>in rebus metus cauſa geſtis,</hi> ſuch a <hi>vitium reale,</hi> for ever nor againſt all ſingular Succeſſors; and ſuppoſing there had been juſt cauſe of fear in this caſe, as there could be none, it were but an unjuſt wreaſting of the <hi>Roman Law,</hi> to the plain prejudice of the Clerks, to give the Petitioner the benefit of that Edict, the effect of which againſt ſingular Succeſſors was at firſt but Annual, ending with every Pretor's Authority, and thereafter endured no longer, even <hi>in rebus immobilibus,</hi> then for the Ten years of the <hi>Roman Praeſcription,</hi> and to refuſe the Clerks, the benefit of that Ten Years <hi>Preſcription,</hi> which (conſidering that their Rights have been <hi>bona fide</hi> acquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and poſſeſt be them and their Authors for <hi>fourteen Years</hi> together, without a ſhaddow of interruption) would ſettle and ſecure the ſame according to the <hi>Roman Law,</hi> beyond all poſſible controverſie.</p>
            <p>The third defence founded on the recording of his <hi>Majeſties Letter,</hi> the Clerks conſent, and all theſe publick Acts of Sederunt, and Parliament mentioned therein; and the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners ſo long acquieſcence and not quarelling the ſame, meets with no other Reply then that it is a quible on the <hi>l. geſta: cod: dere jud:</hi> to apply it to any other thing then to the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Depoſitions of Parties and Witneſſes, and that the recording any Tranſaction or Matter in it ſelf defective cannot ſupply its defects.</p>
            <p>To which it is Duplyed, that it would appear the Replyers common ſenſe in Applying of that Law goes no farder then his Gloſs and Commentars led him, otherways he could not overſee the Import of the word <hi>(Geſtum)</hi> in his ſo much boaſted Edict, <hi>Quod metus cauſa geſtum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>ll:</hi> 19. and 58. <hi>ff. de verb ſignif.</hi> Are the beſt Commentars for the meaning of that word, which make it to ſignifie any Deed that can be the foundation of a Right; and it was not reaſonable to think, that the recording Depoſitions of Parties, and Witneſſes ſhould intereſs the publick Faith more, or put ſingular Succeſſors in greater ſecurity in Relation to the ſubject matter of ſuch Depoſitions, then the Recording publick Reſcripts of Princes, and ſolemn Acts of Sederunt, and Acts of Parliament ſhould do in Relation to what is defined and enacted thereby. And albeit the <hi>Diſcharge</hi> and <hi>Renuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to <hi>Hayſtoun,</hi> on payment of ſo conſiderable a Sum, be the likeſt thing of any to a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action; yet it is hoped that the KING's Letter for executing the Law, the expreſs and judicial conſent of the three Clerks who had then the ſole Right, and the ſeveral Acts
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180207:3"/>
of Sederunt Recorded, and whereupon the Clerks Rights are founded, will not be found matters in themſelves defective; and tho' they ſhould, the two Acts of Parliament cannot; So that without the higheſt Violation of the publick Faith, that can be made in reference to private Rights, and moſt unjuſt Derogation, to the uncontraverted Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, there can be no queſtion of the Rights of the preſent Clerks to their reſpective Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which were bought as dear, and have as many clear and ſolemn Laws for their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as any ſo much property within the Nation.</p>
            <p>To Elide the 4th and 5th Defences, founded upon the <hi>Homologation</hi> and <hi>Renunciation;</hi> There is a forced Bogle of a <hi>Concuſſion</hi> pretended, and a laborious Conceſſion of Citations thrown in, as if the antiquated Name of <hi>Caldas</hi> were as uſeful in Lawyers debates to perſwade the wiſdom of the Nation; as the <hi>Jargon</hi> of <hi>Album Grecum,</hi> and the like; is to raiſe the value of that precious <hi>Drugge;</hi> But becauſe all, or moſt of the Citations, do not at all ſerve to clear, that there was any Fear or Concuſſion in this Caſe, and only prove that Deeds extorted by Force and Fear, are reduceable in Law, which is not the queſtion; And likewayes, that the Replyer pretending to explain the true cauſes and effects of Fear has after his manner wandered far from theſe Cauſes of Fear, which the Law has fixed: Therefore paſſing theſe Citations which concern not the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, let the Legal Cauſes of that <hi>Juſtus Metus,</hi> which by the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, gave the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Reſtitution be conſidered, as they are defined by the Text it ſelf, which is ſo clear, that it leaves no ground of debate, and plainly excludes the Petitioner's Caſe; For the <hi>l:</hi> 3: and what follows in the Title <hi>ff: Quod metus cauſa, &amp;c.</hi> Determines concerning the juſt cauſes of Fear in theſe words: <hi>Continet igitur haec clauſula &amp; vim &amp; metum, &amp; ſi quis vi compulſus aliquid fecit per hoc edictum reſtituitur.</hi> §: 1. <hi>ſed vim accipimus atrocem, &amp; eam quae adverſus bonos mores fiat, non eam quam Magiſtratus recte jutulit, ſcilicet jure licito, &amp; jure ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris quem ſuſtinet.</hi> (which is the very Caſe) <hi>Caeterum ſi per injuriam quid fecit populi Romani, Magiſtratus vel Provinciae Praeſes.</hi> Pomponius <hi>ſcripſit hoc edictum locum habere, ſi forte inquit mortis vel verberum terrore pecuniam alicui extorſerit.</hi> l: 4: <hi>Ego pato etiam ſervitutis timorem ſimuliumque admittendum.</hi> l: 5: <hi>Metum accipiendum</hi> Labeo <hi>dicii non quemlibet timorem, ſed majoris malitatis.</hi> l: 6. <hi>Metum autem non vani hominis, ſed qui merito, &amp; in hominem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſſimum cadat ad hoc Edictum pertinere dicemus.</hi> l: 7. <hi>Nec timorem in famiae hoc Edicto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineri,</hi> Paedius <hi>dicit, neque alicujus vexationis timorem per hoc edictum reſtitui, proinde ſi quis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuloſus rem nullam fruſtra timuerit per hoc edictum non reſtituitur quoniam neque vi neque metus cauſa factum eſt, proinde ſi quis in furto vel adulterio deprehenſus, vel in alio flagitio, vel dedit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, vel ſe obligavit.</hi> Pomponius <hi>recte ſcribit, poſſe eum ad hoc edictam pertinere, timuit enim, vel mortem, vel vincula.</hi> l: 8: §. 2. <hi>Quod ſi dederit ne ſtuprum patiatur Vir ſeu Mulier, hoc edictum locum habet, cum Viris bonis iſte metus major quam mortis eſſe debet.</hi> l: 9. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum autem preſentem accipere debemus, non ſuſpicionem inferendi ejus</hi> (as might have been in this Caſe) <hi>Et ita</hi> Pompomus <hi>ſcribit, Ait enim metum illatum accipiendum, id eſt, Si illatus eſt timor ab aliquo denique tractat, ſi fundum meum dereliquero audito quod quis cum armis veniret, an huic edicte locus ſit, &amp; refert</hi> Labeonem <hi>exiſtimare edicto locum non eſſe &amp; unde vi interdictum ceſſare, quoniam non videor vi dejectus qui dejici non expectavi ſed profugi.</hi> And <hi>Cujacius</hi> on the ſaid L: 7: defines in ſo many words, <hi>Non quilibet m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180207:4"/>
cauſam dat Edicto, ſed mortis aut verberum, aut vinculorum, aut ſervitutis, aut ſtupri ex qua animus conſternatur;</hi> And <hi>Antonius Faber ad dictam, L:</hi> 9: is of the ſame opinion, if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of theſe two may be compared with that of the Replyer, and the ſame <hi>Faber, ad l: all: Eod:</hi> is poſitive, <hi>quod facto opus eſt, &amp; quidem atroci &amp; majoris melitatis ad hoc ut vis facta vel metus illatus dici poſſit.</hi> By all which it is clear as Light, that the <hi>Roman Law</hi> gave Reſtitution againſt no other fear than that of Death, Scourging, Fetters, Slavery, and Raviſhing; And it will be as clear, That the Petitioner could be under no juſt fear of any of theſe, if it be conſidered; 1mo, That albeit his <hi>Majeſties Letter</hi> had made particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mention of him, and his Office, and that he had never ſo good Right to it; Yet in that caſe, the loſs of his Office was no juſt cauſe of Fear, ſo as to infer Reſtitution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Renounciation: How much leſs? when in that Letter he was not ſo much as named. And if neither the fear of Infamy, nor of any other Vexation, fell under the Edict, as a <hi>juſtus metus,</hi> which is expreſly defined in the above Text, it is not intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible how the parting with an illegal pretence, to an Office that coſt him nothing, and for no leſs than Seven Thouſand Merks, can be reckoned a juſt cauſe of Fear; in the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, occaſioned by a Letter, wherein there is not ſo much as one word of him. 2do: Albeit the Letter had contained a threatning of his Majeſties diſpleaſure againſt ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as the Lords ſhould think fit to remove, if they ſhould refuſe either to remove, or accept of the Modification; Yet that could infer no Reſtitution on the Edict, <hi>quod metus cauſa, nam metum non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>actationibus tantum vel conteſtationibus, ſed atrocitate facti probari convenit; l:</hi> 9: <hi>cod: de his qui vi.</hi> 3tio: As his Majeſty, and the Lords in this caſe, ſhewed not the leaſt diſreſpect to any of theſe perſons who were removed at that time; ſo it is impoſſible <hi>per rerum naturam,</hi> that they could have deſigned either by that Letter, or Act of Sederunt, any other thing then their Removal, and the obſerving of the Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, there being no manner of Certification adjected, in caſe of their not accepting the Modification; So that no confidence ſhort of the Petitioners, could obtrude ſuch a groundleſs pretext of Fear, to which he is able to give no other foundation then his own meer conjectures anent his Majeſties diſpleaſure, to convell ſo lucrative and voluntar a tranſaction on his part; And after fourteen years ſilence to quarrel ſingular Succeſſors, for moſt Onerous Cauſe, in their Rights to an Office, ſo ſolemnly ſecured to them, and their Authors both by the publick Law, and his own private Paction.</p>
            <p>The firſt of the two Texts, which were thought fit to be cited in the Replyes, is in <hi>l:</hi> 6: §, 7: <hi>ff: de acquir: vel omit: haered: eum qui metu verborum vel aliquo timore coactus fallens adierit haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſive liber ſit, haeredem non fieri placet ſive ſervus ſit dominum haeredem non facere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this it is Duplyed. 1mo. That the <hi>Aditio Haereditatis,</hi> being the engaging a Perſon in an Affair, which of its own Nature is of the greateſt import, and the moſt involved that is known in Law, ſince it is almoſt Impoſſible for any Man to know diſtinctlie the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum jus, Quod defunctus habuit,</hi> before he enter Heir, and for which cauſe the <hi>dies Cretionis,</hi> and <hi>Au nus Deliberandi,</hi> were introduced to leſſen that danger; it is therefore moſt probable that the <hi>Romans</hi> were more prone and readie to allow Reſtitution againſt the <hi>Aditio Haereditatis,</hi> and upon more ſlender Grounds then againſt any other Obligation in their Law, and it is certain that in our Deciſions the Lords do frequentlie ſuſtaine defences to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180207:4"/>
Elide an Odious paſſive Title, which they would repell in other cauſes, for the whole context of the Civil Law, anent the Edict, <hi>Quod metus cauſa</hi> makes that paragraph alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether excentrick and Irregular. But 2do. the great <hi>Cujace;</hi> whom never Man after <hi>Juſtinian's</hi> time equaled in the knowledge of the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, was ſo conſcious to the abſolute inconſiſtency of this Text, with the whole Titles, <hi>Quod metus cauſa</hi> both in the <hi>digeſt: &amp; Cod.</hi> That he is forced in his Comentar, <hi>ad. l:</hi> 21. §: 5. <hi>Digeſtis quod metus cauſa</hi> to correct it, and in ſtead of <hi>Verborum</hi> to Read it <hi>Verberum:</hi> For (ſays he) <hi>metus eſt futurorum &amp; ſic dicimus metum verberum qui juſtus eſt, metus non verborum:</hi> So that this Text being thus reſtored will not meet the caſe; ſeing if the <hi>alique timore,</hi> which follows the word <hi>verberum</hi> be not likewiſe corrupted, it muſt be underſtood <hi>habili modo,</hi> &amp; neceſſarly ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be always a <hi>juſtus timor, ſcilicet ex juſta cauſa;</hi> and it is pleaſant to take notice that the Replyer could not find one ſingle <hi>grue</hi> in all the Bodie of the Civill Law, which could be wreaſted ſo much to favour the Petitioners caſe ſave this corrupt Text only, and yet tho it were ſincere, as it cannot be; He could not ſubſume in the terms of it, neither the King nor the Lords having by Word or Write threatned the Petitioner to accept of the Money or to grant the <hi>Renunciation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Citation is the <hi>l:</hi> 11. <hi>Cod. de his quae vi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Si per impreſſionem quis aliquem metueus ſaltem in mediocri officio conſtitutum rei ſuae in eadem provincia, vel loco ubitale officium peragit, ſub venditionis titulo fecerit Ceſſionem quod emptum fuit reddatur.</hi> Upon which Text the Replyer moſt inſipidly ſubſums, That in the Petitioners caſe, there was <hi>aliquis metus,</hi> for a Child would have adverted that the word <hi>aliquem</hi> in the Text, could not conſtrue with <hi>impreſſionem,</hi> and did refer only to the Concuſtor, and he is pleaſed to add that the Petitioner could not have diſobeyed the Kings command in his Letter, without the haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of being conſtructed a ſeditious Contemner of Authority; ſo that his taking the Money was an Act of neceſſity.</p>
            <p>It is Replyed, That the Impreſſion mentioned, there behoved to have been a juſt one from a ſufficient Cauſe; And albeit in this Text, which is acknowledged to be <hi>ſincere,</hi> the word <hi>aliquem</hi> had been written <hi>aliquam,</hi> as the Replyer would have it: Yet the Law even in that caſe would regulate the Extent of that general Terme, and reſtrict it only to a juſt impreſſion, the cauſes of which are fixed and known in Law; And as it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Cauſes of Juſt Fear defined in the Text, as well as from the <hi>l:</hi> 10: <hi>cod: hoc tit:</hi> in theſe words, <hi>accuſationis inſtitutae vel futurae metu alienationem ſeu promiſſionem factam reſcindi poſtulantis improbum eſt deſiderium.</hi> That the hazard of being conſtructed a ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Contemner of Authority was no cauſe of fear, to which the <hi>Roman Law</hi> would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the benefit of the Edict, unleſs he ſhould thereby have run the hazard of being truly guilty of <hi>Sedition:</hi> So it is groſs to alleadge that the Kings Letter bears a command to the Petitioner for accepting of Money, or Relates to him otherwiſe then as the Lords of Seſſion ſhould find juſt to apply it; but in this caſe there is no difficulty to underſtand that the Petitioner was abundantly ſecure from the hazard of contemning Authority, by his forbearing to intrude any more upon that Office, and ſuffering the Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to be put to execution, whether he had accepted of Money for ſo doing, or granted any ſuch Renounciation or not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:180207:5"/>By all which it is plain, that none of theſe Citations that are adduced out of <hi>Baldus, Anchoranus, Fulgoſius, Geminus, Pappon: Caldas, Natta, Alexander, Arretinus, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochius,</hi> and <hi>Bartolus</hi> are to the purpoſe; And in the caſe the Lady <hi>Gray</hi> againſt the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> the Right tranſmitted by the Lady, was a Legal Right conſiſtent with Law, the Concuſſor was called and inſiſted againſt, and there were Acts of Force and Violence lybelled and proven; ſuch as that the Earl violently entred to the poſſeſſion of theſe Lands, diſponed before any ſentence in his Favours or Right made to him be the Lady. Whereas in this Caſe, tho' the Petitioner's Right had not been null by the Act of Parliament; yet there was no Force or Violence done for removing him, much leſs was he any wayes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to accept of Money, or give ſuch an expreſs Renunciation of his Right; and if he had been intimidate by the LORDS to accept of the Money, as he was not; yet a Receipt of the ſeven Thouſand Merks, had anſwered the Termes of the Act of Sederunt, by which he is not at all ordained to Renunce: And he might upon offering to conſigne ſuch a Receipt without the <hi>Renunciation,</hi> have oblieged <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> to pay the Sum by a Charge on the Act of Sederunt, upon which, albeit it be plainly and poſitively urged, that on the other Hand no manner of Execution could have followed againſt the Petitioner, if he had not volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarly both given Obedience and Renunced; yet nevertheleſs, there is no Reply made to this, but that in thoſe days he durſt not offer to repoſſeſs himſelf of his Office, as it is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceived he dare not now a dayes, albeit he might then as well as now, refuſe or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Money, and grant Renunciations or not, as he thought fit.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Allegeance againſt the <hi>Concuſſion,</hi> That the LORDS had no intereſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs, gets no better Reply; For to ſay the KING concuſſed, eſpecially in an Affair where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Petitioner's particular Intereſt was not conſidered, and which might have taken full effect without his accepting of Money, and all without his giving any ſuch Renunciation, does not at all take it off, and therefore needs no farther Duply.</p>
            <p>To the thrid on the ſpecial Caſe of ſingular Succeſſors. It is Replyed, That the Action of Reſtitution competent to the Party laeſed, is in <hi>Rem ſcripta,</hi> and follows the thing extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whatever <hi>Bona Fides</hi> the poſſeſſor had in the acquiſition.</p>
            <p>It is Duplyed, That this Allegiance does not grant, but only ſuppoſe the Concuſſion; and if the Replyer had been ingenuous enough in citing the Law, it had cleared the point: For when in his Reply to the Dilators, he cites, <hi>l:</hi> 14: §: 3. <hi>ff. quod met. cauſa.</hi> After the words; <hi>In hac actione non quaeritur utrum iſqui convinitur au alius metum fecit, ſufficit enim hoc docere metum ſibi illatum eſſe.</hi> He induſtriouſly ſuppreſſes theſe which immediatly follow, <hi>Et ex haere eum qui convenitur etſi crimine caret lucrum tamen ſenſiſſe.</hi> Which words do not only quite exclude this Caſe from falling under that edict, ſeing the Clerks have their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for moſt Onerous Cauſes, as is notour to all concerned, and ſo cannot in Law be ſaid <hi>Lucrum ſenſiſſe;</hi> But likewayes theſe words muſt ſecure all ſuch ſingular Succeſſors from the Avarice of evil Men, whoſe pretences they could not poſſibly obviat, and what is ſaid before to enforce the ſecond Defence, as to the difference of <hi>res furtiva,</hi> and <hi>metu geſta,</hi> in relation to ſingular Succeſſors is here repeated, tho' it be ſufficiently cleared by what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid, That the Petitioner was under no Impreſſion whereof the Law takes notice.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is Replyed, to the 4th: Allegiance. That the Renounciation being granted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180207:5"/>
while the King who ſigned that Letter was in life, And the Petitioner within his reach; The Renounciation ought in Law to be looked on as an effect of the ſame continued Awe and Force, whereby he was removed; And the ſame as if Robbers had plundered him of an hundred pounds, and offered back ten on his Diſcharge of the whole, in which caſe the Diſcharge could not hinder Reſtitution.</p>
            <p>It is Duplyed, 1mo: Although the Letter had expreſly commanded him, to remove from his Office, yet unleſs it had adjected a certification of Death, or an or other, of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove effects of the <hi>vis atrox,</hi> defined in the Text, it could import none of the Legal and fixt cauſes of <hi>juſtus metus,</hi> But its far otherwiſe, and that Letter is intended and conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch terms, as could not poſſible fright any Rational Man, And it is not in the leaſt queſtioned, but the Petitioner (if he had not been conſcious to the nullity of his Gift, as being grounded on that diſpenſing clauſe, in expreſs contradiction to the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and conſtitution mentioned in that Letter) he would have refuſed to accept of the money, and without delay would have applyed to the King, to be reponed, who as the Petitioner cannot deny, looked on him at that time as a very Loyal Subject, and wanted but ſuch an occaſion to reward the Faithful Sacrifice he conſtantly rendred to him during the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Uſurpation. But 2do: The Letter and Act of Sederunt were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently obtempered by his removing; and if he was thereby bound to give a Receipt to <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> on payment of the Seven Thouſand Merks, which is not unqueſtionable, yet it is plain beyond all contradiction, that there was no neceſſity from that Letter, or the Act following upon it, either for his accepting of the Money; or after he had taken it for his granting ſo poſitive and ample a Renounciation in terms ſufficient, both to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nude himſelf, and to tranſmit his pretence in favours of others; tho the Letter and Act of Sederunt had left his pretended Right as entire as it was at the firſt granting of it; and as to the ungentle parallel of the Robbers, there are ſo many diſparities, and ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, that it merits no more Particular anſwer then that the Petitioner is not in the caſe of the Edict, and tho he were, the difference in Law betwixt <hi>Res metu geſtae</hi> and <hi>res furtivae</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſingullar ſuceſſors for moſt onerous Cauſes, and Robbers need not be inſiſted upon.</p>
            <p>The Replyer ends with a Reflection on the Wrongs commited in the latter Reigns, as if the diſpenſing clauſe in Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſes</hi> Gift, and be vertue whereof he appointed ſix Clerks of Seſſion, in manifeſt contempt of the Act of Parliament, were not one of the moſt pregnant inſtances, though nor the moſt important, that can be obſerved of that Nature, ſince the Reſtoration of the Monarchy; and was a wrong done not to a ſingle Perſon only, but to that intire Fraternity, &amp; the making a preparative to break that Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and thereby occaſion the greateſt diſorders in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice in all time thereafter, if the Regiſters thought fit to conſtitut as many Clerks of Seſſion as the Secretaries of State are in uſe to admit Writers to the Signet, which they might very well have done be vertue of that Clauſe, if the King could have thereby diſpenſed with the Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, 1621. Although it be but conſonant to the Modeſty of the Replyer to obtrude that the Kings letter for Executing the Act of Parliament was an act of Tyrrany; and yet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180207:6"/>
that Clauſe was a deed of legall Adminiſtration becauſe it is the Foundation of the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners pretended Right who does very much diſparage the ſufferings of theſe Perſons in whoſe favours Their MAJESTIES and the ESTATES paſt the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for Reſcinding Fynes and Forefaulturers, by ſo Whinning a Compariſon of the merits of his cauſe; for tho his MAJESTIES Commiſſioner had not in plain Parliament Ordered the Petitioners Caſe to be Expunged out of that Act, it is very well known that he never ſuffered the leaſt inconveniencie <hi>for Conſcience ſake;</hi> Nor will any Man who has not <hi>darkned that Light by Self-love and Avarice, pretend to an Office;</hi> which after he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed for ſeveral years without paying a Groat for it; He then Renounced upon Receipt of <hi>Seven Thouſand Merks;</hi> And knows very well that the preſent Clerks, whom he would now <hi>Rob of it,</hi> did purchaſe it <hi>bona fide, for a greater Sum;</hi> And whereof (if he ſhould prevail) they have no Action competent to them for Recovery of a Sixpence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Reſpect whereof, The deſire of the Petition ought to be Refuſed, and the Petitioner condemned in ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes as the Honourable Lords and other Members of the</hi> Commiſſion of Parliament, <hi>ſhall find juſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:180207:6"/>
            <head>THE VISCOUNT OF TARBAT Being Cited INCIDENTER in the Action betwixt <hi>Alexander Monro,</hi> and the Clerks of the SESSION; Does humbly Offer what followes to be Conſidered by the Right Honourable COMMISSION of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>BY The expreſs ſtanding Statutes, the Clerk Regiſter's Deputes for <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Seſſion,</hi> are reſtricted to the number of Three. The Law prohibites the Clerk Regiſter to commiſſionat any more; or to adjoine any to theſe Three, without expreſs conſent of the other Principal to whom any ſhall be adjoined.</p>
            <p>Some three or four times, one deſires of the Principals; one has been adjoined to the Deſirer before the year 1640, and this was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to Law. But Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> caſts in a Clauſe in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion allowing him to joine one or more in theſe Offices, as ſhould be found conducing to the good of the Leidges; and on this warrand joins one to every one of the Three Offices, ratifies their Gifts in Parliament, and they ſerve in Seſſion; but without asking or getting any expreſs conſent of the other Three, as the Law does <hi>ſpecifickly</hi> require; and amongſt others, Mr <hi>Monro</hi> is adjoined to Mr <hi>John Hay Gratis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1764, The KING being informed, that this was againſt Law, and (as ſome ſaid) inconvenient, He by a Royal Letter to the Seſſion, as a juſt Executor of the Law, requires the Lords to reduce theſe Offices to their lawful Conſtitution and Number; But accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to His <hi>Clement Nature,</hi> did alſo preſcribe, that theſe who in conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180207:7"/>
to Law were to be removed, ſhould have a Gratification given by the other who was to remain in each Office, at ſuch a rate, as the ſupreme Judicature of the Nation ſhould judge fit: The Seſſion giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dutiful Obedience to the Royal Will, in reducing this matter to the Rule of the Law; They modifie no leſs, then the full of what was by cuſtom payed for ſuch an Adjuncts Office at, or before that time; <hi>viz.</hi> 7000 <hi>Merks</hi> to each.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt theſe who were judged fitteſt to be removed, would rather have kept their illegal poſſeſſion, then take this ſum: But they could not but think their removal was ordered with <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> when as by Law, they might have been ſet off from their illegal Poſſeſſion without the reimburſment of their inconſiderable Advance; yet to be re-imburſed of it, and enjoy their gain whilſt they poſſeſt, tho to the <hi>Laeſion</hi> of the other Clerks, on whom they were intruded, and accordingly they went off in acquieſcence.</p>
            <p>But if two who bought their Office did ſo, how well ſatisfied ſhould <hi>Mr: Monro</hi> have been, who not only entered illegally, and more ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally than the other two; but alſo <hi>gratis?</hi> And albeit he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have kept the Office, yet he ſhewed full acquieſcence; 1. By uſing no Proteſtation nor interpellation to the ſentence; 2. By homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating it, in receiving the Price. 3. By a <hi>Legal Diſpoſition of all ſuch Right &amp; Title as he had, to another.</hi> And 4 by acquieſcing for 14 years in this tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action. And 5 by a voluntar exercing another Office in that very Court, inconſiſtent with his being a Clerk. <hi>viz.</hi> Of an Advocate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Proteſtation or Inſinuation, that he had ſo much as any pretence or an eye to the Clerkſhip. One who were not verſed in the Novel of Mr <hi>Monro's</hi> Replyes, and knew nothing but Law and Reaſon, would think that if there was Injury done to any in all this Affair, it was to Mr <hi>John Hay,</hi> on whoſe Office Mr <hi>Monro</hi> was obtruded; And when the KING reſtored him to his Right, that yet he behoved to pay for this Juſtice, and to one who had no legal Tittle to it, and who gave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for it, had Mr <hi>Monro</hi> ſo much of pretence, it had ſav'd his <hi>Lawyers</hi> the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180207:7"/>
expences of a great deal of miſtake, both in <hi>citation and application of Laws</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However Mr <hi>Hay</hi> goes from the Office, Sir <hi>Thomas Murray</hi> being Clerk Regiſter, what ſhould now be done? A Clerk is neceſſar for the Kingdom, and exerciſe of Juſtice; Mr <hi>Monro</hi> puts in no claime on his notable Tittle, and I dare ſay, Sir <hi>Thomas Murray</hi> did not gueſs that he could not place one in that Office, without hazard of being a <hi>Concuſsor,</hi> a <hi>Robber,</hi> or ſome other of the Replyer's <hi>Epithets.</hi> In the name of ſport, the Clerks place muſt vaik till Mr <hi>Monro</hi> think fit to deſire it, or until he ſit down in his Chair: Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> did not know this Obligation, he Commiſſionates another whom he and the Seſſion judged fit, and receives a good deed for it <hi>viz.</hi> 100 Pieces more then Mr <hi>John Hay</hi> did give for the half of it to Mr <hi>Monro.</hi> He ſerves the Leid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but what's payed him for his Service? He muſt by this New Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured Logick, pay it in to Mr <hi>Monro</hi> who Served none, Interpelled none, and Exerced two other lucrative Imployments at the time, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with this Service of a Clerk: And not only ſo, but to the as good, he muſt remove and yield his Place to Mr <hi>Monro,</hi> I hope under the pain of Quadruple: For ſo the Edict preſcribes againſt the unwilling Reſtorer; and no doubt, the now Clerks are not frank to Reſtore haſtily.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>Tarbat</hi> as the Replyer doth ſhortly call him, comes thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be Clerk Regiſter, and in his time Actions were multiplyed, and it was judged by many not unfit that there ſhould be two in every Office. <hi>Tarbat</hi> adviſes it, and finds the Judges of this Opinion, He Repreſents it to the King, who gives his Conſent, but ſo as by a Letter, to lay it before the <hi>ſupreme Judicature,</hi> who found that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſtanding Law this could not be done without the conſent of the Three who were in Office, and they conſenting, Three were adjoyned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tarbat</hi> did not by Vertue of a Clauſe contrait to a ſtanding Act of Parliament, take a Liberty to add one or more in theſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; But <hi>Tarbat</hi> according to the Law, did add one to each, with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180207:8"/>
the conſent of him, to whom he was added; And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Clauſe creept in to the Clerk Regiſters Commiſſions was no narrower than to allow him to add one or more; <hi>Tarbat</hi> did take care in the Act of Parliament 1685, That <hi>the power of Adding, tho with conſent, ſhould not exceed one of Addition;</hi> And all this while <hi>Tarbat</hi> can Declare, he never heard or thought of Mr. <hi>Monro</hi> as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be a Principal or Adjunct.</p>
            <p>Now, How comes <hi>Tarbat</hi> to be called or concerned in this Proceſs? if it be for Reſtitution of what was payed to him, in caſe of Evicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he proteſts to be heard againſt that in time convenient, ſince on hitherto uncontraverted grounds of Law, he will make it evident, that <hi>non tenetur de evictione,</hi> of what he got, <hi>quatenus in officio;</hi> and that againſt the Repetition when urged.</p>
            <p>But he preſumes it Legally impoſſible, That Deputes can be in the leaſt hazard from ſo wild a Claim, not only not founded but oppoſite to all Law, Juſtice, and Reaſon. And is far from doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That the Right Honourable Court of Parliament, will take ſevere Animadverſion of ſo ſcandalous and calumnious Plea's; which indeed as much as in the Pretender lyes, reflects as far on the Juſtice of that Court, as can poſſibly be done, by bringing ridiculous Claims to vex the Leiges; As if that High Court could not ſoon diſcern what every Perſon of common ſenſe, cannot but diſcern; As to which Lybel and Replyes ſo full of the darkeſt miſtakes of Law, and Lawy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſo ſtuft with <hi>Paralogiſms</hi> in <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Solaeciſms</hi> in <hi>Grammar;</hi> He will make no Anſwer, that being with far more Learning, nor is proportionable, fully made by the Clerks in their Anſwers, and Duplies to the Petition and Replies. And albeit he knows himſelf not reachable in the particular; yet your Lordſhips will, I hope, allow him to expoſtulat for redreſs againſt ſuch Injuries, to Subjects, to Laws, and to our <hi>Soveraignes;</hi> For as to our ſelves perhaps Record cannot inſtance ſo calumnious a Plea. Sometimes the Adverſaries gives their Action the name of <hi>Concuſſion,</hi> another time of <hi>Quod metus cauſa;</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180207:8"/>
ſofurth. I may ſay with <hi>Cato in ſaluſt. Jam pridem equidem nos vera rerum vocabula amiſimus,</hi> If there was Concuſſion? will the Poſſeſſor <hi>ſine cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> be decerned againſt before a Concuſſion be proved? And can a Concuſſion be proved Judicially, without ſo much as citing a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſor? For they are not yet ſo ridiculous, as to alleage that the now Clerks were the Concuſſors: Well, if they miſs of a Concuſſion, it muſt be found reduceable <hi>ex capite metus;</hi> But where is the Violence? not ſo much as one threat alleaged to dimit the Office, no, not a Legal Execution, nor poſſibility of one to force an Homologation: And yet both Dimiſſion, Diſpoſition, and Homologation, ſo voluntarly granted without a ſhaddow of Coaction, muſt be reduced <hi>ex capite metus:</hi> Is not this unparellel'd calumnie, and ridiculing of our Laws, intollerablie! But to make up all, Concuſſion, Violence, Robbery; And all the <hi>Black Names</hi> is ſum'd up at laſt, by the Replyer, in this. <hi>It was done by the Letter of a King,</hi> who becauſe he writes to his Senate, to Reduce Enormities and illegal Invaſions of Rights, to, and according to the Standing Laws, and that by no <hi>extrajudicial Edict,</hi> nor new <hi>erected Court,</hi> nor <hi>extraordinary Commiſſion,</hi> but by the <hi>Ordinar Supreme,</hi> and <hi>beſt loved Court of the Nation:</hi> So far from ſhewing Anger at the Perſons; that in Rectifying the wrong, he gratifies them by Reward, rather than Puniſhment; And ſo far from Threats, that Gentler Expreſſions could not be Adapted, to excuſe the faults of a Child, than was uſed by this <hi>Father of the Country</hi> to theſe tranſgreſſors of his Law; But this is treated with no more Civil Name, then <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion;</hi> And in plain Terms a KING! for ſo <hi>Juſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Clement,</hi> ſo <hi>moderate,</hi> ſo <hi>beneficial execution of the Juſt Laws,</hi> is branded with the expreſs Character of a <hi>Concuſſor,</hi> a <hi>Robber,</hi> a <hi>Tyrant!</hi> which touching ſo rudely on the <hi>lawful exerciſe of the Soveraign Power,</hi> as not only to Defame a late <hi>Glorious King,</hi> Uncle to both Their MAJESTIES; But with a moſt Criminal Inſolence, to <hi>Pannel Kingſhip!</hi> And to Attacque the <hi>Monarchie</hi> in its moſt Eminent Rights. Therefore to conclude, The <hi>Viſcount of Tarbat,</hi> Does Humbly Intreat Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180207:9"/>
to conſider this Invaſion of the <hi>Royal Honour</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter worthie of Your Notice; And Deſires that no Progreſs be made in this matter, which wholly depends on the <hi>Kings Soveraign Power;</hi> And the Execution thereof until His <hi>Majeſty</hi> be informed of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this purſute, wherein His Honour, and the <hi>Right of the Crown</hi> is ſo deeply concerned. And Humbly Offers, and Propoſes as a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, a Peer, and a Member of Parliament, That His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, Solicitor, or their Subſtitutes, may be conſulted in ſo high a Point; And that inquiry be made for the Authors of this ſcandalous, Criminal Lybell; And further, Humbly Offers to Yours Lordſhips Conſideration, if the Cauſe do not require, that the Authors and Spreaders be ſecured, untill His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Pleaſure be known herein.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180207:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
